{"tossups": [{"question": "This \"people of the flint\" were the target of missionary efforts by Johannes Megapolensis [[yoh-HAH-ness meh-guh-poh-LEN-siss]] and earlier battled Hurons under the command of Samuel de Champlain. Due to claiming lands along a namesake river valley west of the Hudson River, this group was known as the Keepers of the Eastern Door. For ten points, name this member tribe of the Iroquois [[IH-roh-kwoy]] Confederacy, known in popular culture for an incorrectly attributed hairstyle in which the sides of the head are shaven.", "answer": "<b><u>Mohawk</u></b>s (or <b><u>Kanien\u02bckeh\u00e1</u><u>\ua789</u><u>ka</u></b>; accept <b><u>Keepers of the Eastern Door</u></b> before mentioned; prompt on \"Iroquois\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "As punishment for smoking, Deccan [[DEH-kan]] sultan Malik Ambar poured this substance into the ears and mouths of criminals. The Piazza Fontana bombings occurred during a tumultuous time in Italian history known as the \"Years of [this substance].\" This substance's presence in Roman toys and plumbing has been speculated as a cause of the fall of the Roman Empire due to widespread impotence and ill health effects. For ten points, name this toxic metal symbolized Pb.", "answer": "<b><u>Lead</u></b> (accept <b><u>Pb</u></b> before mentioned; accept Years of <b><u>Lead</u></b>; accept Anni di <b><u>piombo</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During a performance in this country of the ballet <em>Spartacus</em> by Aram Khachaturian [[kah-chah-TOO-ree-ahn]], Leonid Yakobson [[YAH-kohb-sun]] abandoned the traditional <em>pointe</em> technique during a performance at the Bolshoi Theatre. Ethnically Polish dancer Vaslav Nijinsky [[nih-JIN-skee]] helped popularize a ballet company named for this nation originally founded by Sergei Diaghilev [[dee-AH-geh-lef]]. Unrest occurred during the ballet <em>The Rite of Spring</em>, composed by, for ten points, what nation's composer, Igor Stravinsky?", "answer": "<b><u>Russia</u></b> (accept <b><u>Russia</u></b>n Empire; accept <b><u>Soviet Union</u></b>; accept <b><u>USSR</u></b>; or <b><u>U</u></b>nion of <b><u>S</u></b>oviet <b><u>S</u></b>ocialist <b><u>R</u></b>epublics; accept <b><u>CCCP</u></b>; prompt on \"Armenia\"; prompt on \"Georgia\"; NOTE: Khachaturian was born to an Armenian family in modern-day Georgia, but he was a Russian, then Soviet citizen)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Pinaka and Shiranga are this type of weapon in Hindu myth, in which Arjuna [[ar-JOO-nah]] also fights with one of these weapons made by Brahma called Gandiva [[gahn-DEE-vah]]. Hou Yi [[HOH-YEE]] uses one of these weapons in Chinese myth to eliminate nine of the ten suns. The constellation Sagittarius is named after Chiron's [[KY-rons]] role in teaching the use of these weapons to Achilles. Medieval tales abound with legends of users of these weapons from Sherwood Forest. For ten points, name this ranged weapon often featured in mythology.", "answer": "<b><u>Bow</u></b> and Arrows", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "Thomas Young helped decipher this writing system by identifying that cartouches [[kar-TOO-shes]] were used to enclose royal names. Demotic [[dee-MAH-tik]] was a simplified version of Hieratic [[hy-RAH-tik]] cursive, which derived from this writing system. Jean-Fran\u00e7ois Champollion [[shahm-pohl-YOHN]] deciphered this script using an object which depicted a decree in this system as well as Ancient Greek. The Rosetta Stone helped decipher, for ten points, what pictographic writing system of Ancient Egypt?", "answer": "Egyptian <b><u>Hieroglyph</u></b>s (or <b><u>Hieroglyph</u></b>ics)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "In an effort to map this river in the 19th century, Breton explorer Auguste Pavie [[pah-VEE]] led a namesake mission with a convoy of elephants. During the first days of the Tet Offensive, the Vietcong attempted to seize all major towns in South Vietnam along this river. Cambodia, Laos, Thailand, and Vietnam formed a commission to maintain the natural integrity of, for ten points, what river of Southeast Asia?", "answer": "<b><u>Mekong</u></b> River (accept <b><u>Mekong</u></b> River Commission)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Near the end of this decade, Link Wray released the song \u201cRumble,\u201d and Alan Freed\u2019s career tanked due to the Payola scandal. Number one hits in this decade included \u201cThe Ballad of Davy Crockett,\u201d \u201cLove Me Tender,\u201d and \u201cLa Bamba.\u201d At this decade\u2019s end, a plane crash called \u201cThe Day the Music Died\u201d resulted in the deaths of Richie Valens, The Big Bopper, and Buddy Holly. For ten points, name this decade in which the rock-and-roll hit \"Heartbreak Hotel\" became a number one hit for Elvis Presley.", "answer": "19<b><u>50</u></b>s", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "A victim of one of these attacks attempted to fold one thousand origami cranes to rid herself of a perpetual illness caused by one of these events, the orders for which were transmitted by General Thomas T. Handy. The Flying Fortress <em>Enola Gay</em> dropped a payload known as the \"Little Boy\" during the first of these events. For ten points, name these attacks by the United States on Japan, the only recorded nuclear bombings in history.", "answer": "<b><u>Atomic Bomb</u></b>ings of Hiroshima and Nagasaki (accept <b><u>Atomic Bomb</u></b>ings of Japan; accept \"Nuclear\" in place of \"Atomic\"; prompt on \"Bombing of Hiroshima and Nagasaki\" or either individual city)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "To criticize a man holding this position, Buzz Windrip, Doremus Jessup uses the periodical <em>The Vermont Vigilance</em> in the Sinclair Lewis novel, <em>It Can't Happen Here</em>. Prior to the events of Philip K. Dick's <em>The Man in the High Castle</em>, the successor of John Nance Garner, John W. Bricker, held this political position but failed to prevent an Axis occupation of North America. Phyllis Wheatley wrote \"To his Excellency General Washington\" about a holder of, for ten points, what executive position?", "answer": "<b><u>President</u></b> of the <b><u>United States</u></b> of America (accept <b><u>American President</u></b>; accept <b><u>U.S.</u></b> in place of <b><u>United States</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A passive walkout-turned-uprising in one of these places in Vorkuta [[vor-KOO-tah]] occurred in response to a mass influx of Ukrainians and the arrest of the repressive NKVD head Lavrentiy Beria [[law-REN-tee BEH-ree-ah]]. The Khrushchev Thaw led to the rehabilitation of many prisoners held in these camps first created by Lenin during the Russian Civil War. Many of the political opponents of the Great Purge were sent to, for ten points, what Soviet forced labor camps prominent in the Stalinist period?", "answer": "<b><u>Gulag</u></b>s (accept <b><u>G</u></b>l\u00e1vnoje <b><u>u</u></b>pravl\u00e9nije <b><u>lag</u></b>er\u00e9j)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "During this war, the Creel Committee sent out \u201cfour minute men\u201d to encourage people to buy war bonds, and during this war, the USFA encouraged \u201cMeatless Mondays.\u201d The Sedition Act passed during this war caused Eugene V. Debs to be jailed for encouraging draft-dodging. A president urged the U.S to enter this war to \u201cmake the world safe for democracy.\u201d For ten points, name this war in which the United States sent \"doughboys\" to fight in the trenches.", "answer": "<b><u>World War One</u></b> (or the <b><u>First World War</u></b>; accept the <b><u>Great War</u></b>; or <b><u>Weltkrieg</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "It's not Portugal, but <em>The Lusiads</em> inspired this nation's opera <em>L'Africaine</em> [[lah-free-KEHN]], about the historical Vasco da Gama. A member of this nation's <em>Les Six</em> [[LEH SEE]] was inspired by the martyrdom of a convent of nuns to write his <em>Dialogues of the Carmelites</em>. The composer of <em>The Carnival of the Animals</em> was from this nation, as was the composer of <em>Clair de Lune</em>. For ten points, name this European nation, home to composers like Camille Saint-Sa\u00ebns [[kah-MEEL san-SAHN]] and Claude Debussy [[klohd deh-byoo-SEE]].", "answer": "<b><u>France</u></b> (accept First <b><u>French</u></b> Empire; accept Second <b><u>French</u></b> Empire; accept <b><u>French</u></b> Second Republic; accept <b><u>French</u></b> Third Republic)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "A peasant rebellion in this nation led by Skipper Clement was put down by the noble Johan Rantzau [[RAHNT-zow]] during the Count's Feud. H\u00e5kon VI [[HAH-kohn the SIXTH]] of Norway married this kingdom's Queen Margaret, leading to the formation of the Kalmar Union. The German Empire seized this country's province of Schleswig [[SHLESS-vig]] in a brief 19th century conflict. For ten points, name this Scandinavian nation that once governed Sweden and Norway from its capital, Copenhagen.", "answer": "Kingdom of <b><u>Denmark</u></b> (or Kongeriget <b><u>Danmark</u></b>; accept the <b><u>Danish</u></b> Realm; or <b><u>Danmark</u></b>s Rige)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This oratorio was based on a text compiled from the Coverdale Psalter and King James Bible by Charles Jennens. Part one of this oratorio depicts the salvation of Isaiah, and that scene in this work is punctuated by <em>And the Glory of the Lord</em>. A popular legend states that George II began the tradition of standing during this piece's <em>Hallelujah Chorus</em>. For ten points, name this oratorio often performed at Christmas, written by George Frideric Handel.", "answer": "<em><b><u>Messiah</u> </b></em>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This group intentionally sparked the Regina [[ruh-JY-nah]] Riots in an attempt to crush a mass protest of unemployed men. This group was able to successfully infiltrate the Communist Party of its nation, and one of this group's most notable accomplishments was capturing stagecoach robber Bill Miner. The nickname of this group derives from their now-defunct standard of riding horses. For ten points, name this police force that is responsible for civil control in Canada.", "answer": "<b><u>Mounties</u></b> (accept <b><u>Royal Canadian Mounted Police</u></b>; accept <b><u>RCMP</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In one of these artworks, a woman labeled \"America First\" reads a children's book titled <em>Adolf the Wolf</em> to impressionable kids. One of these artworks depicts a turtle known as \"O Grab Me\" biting a New Englander holding a barrel labeled \"Super Fine.\" The two symbols of the American political parties, the donkey and elephant, were first introduced through this medium. For ten points, name these graphics that depict public figures, usually expressing the artist's opinion.", "answer": "<b><u>Political Cartoon</u></b>s (prompt on \"Editorial Cartoon\"; prompt on partial answer)  Thomas Nast, perhaps America's most well-known political cartoonist, gained notoriety for his criticism of \"Boss\" Tweed, the leader of what New York political machine that was infamous for its corruption?  ANSWER: <b><u>Tammany</u></b> Hall (or <b><u>Tammany</u></b> Society; accept Society of St. <b><u>Tammany</u></b>; or Sons of St. <b><u>Tammany</u></b>; accept the <b><u>Columbian Order</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A poet from this nation named Pulci [[POOL-chee]] retells an account of Charlemagne\u2019s paladins, Roland [[roh-LAHND]] and Renauld [[reh-NOHD]] who convert the title <em>Morgante</em> [[mor-GAHN-teh]] to Christianity. William of Baskerville solves a murder in a Benedictine monastery in this country in <em>The Name of the Rose</em> by Umberto Eco [[EH-koh]]. Cesare Borgia's [[CHEH-zeh-reh BOR-zhahs]] military exploits inspired Niccolo Machiavelli to write The Prince, in, for ten points, what is now what country?", "answer": "<b><u>Italy</u></b> (accept <b><u>Italian</u></b> Republic; accept <b><u>Italia</u></b>)", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "England's first ambassador to this nation, Thomas Roe, failed to gain special trading privileges in Surat [[soo-RAHT]]. The Afghani Sur Empire temporarily usurped control from this country until the regent Hemu [[HEE-moo]] lost the Second Battle of Panipat [[PAN-ee-pat]]. The rulers of this empire claimed direct descent from Tamerlane, and under Aurangzeb [[oh-RAHNG-zehb]] this empire conquered much of the Deccan [[DEH-kan]] Plateau. Shah Jahan and Akbar ruled, for ten points, what Muslim empire of the Indian subcontinent?", "answer": "<b><u>Mughal</u></b> Empire (or <b><u>Mughal</u></b>s; prompt on \"India\" before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>Jerome Connor created a tribute to the more than 600 nuns who nursed</u></b> <b><u>soldiers during this conflict, and Loreta Janeta Vel\u00e1zquez likely masqueraded as a</u></b> <b><u>male soldier during this conflict. The only woman to ever receive the Medal of (+)</u></b> <b>Honor, Mary Walker, served as a surgeon during this war, as did the founder of the American Red Cross and \"Angel of the Battlefield,\" (*) </b>Clara Barton. For ten points, name this war, during which Belle Boyd provided valuable information to Stonewall Jackson.", "answer": "United States <b><u>Civil War</u></b> (accept War <b><u>Between the States</u></b>; accept War of <b><u>Northern Aggression</u></b>; accept <b><u>American</u></b> or <b><u>U.S.</u></b> in place of \"United States\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>\"Mad Jack\" Churchill entered battle carrying one of these instruments, using it</u></b> <b><u>to signal attack orders to his fellow commandos during operations. James Reid was</u></b> <b><u>executed for playing this instrument during the Battle of Culloden [[kuh-LAH-den]] in</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> the Jacobite [[JAK-oh-bite]] Rising, with the British brandishing this instrument as a \"weapon of war.\" Contemporary historian George Buchanan reports that this aerophonic instrument replaced the trumpet in warfare during in the 1600s. The Highlanders (*) </b>of Scotland introduced, for ten points, which woodwind instrument?", "answer": "<b><u>Bagpipe</u></b>s", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In 1979, the Wetzel [[VEHT-zull]] family escaped East Germany using one of</u></b> <b><u>these objects after years of planning. The first-ever intercontinental ranged weapon</u></b> <b><u>used this technology and was known as</u> </b><em><b><u>Fu-Go</u></b></em><b><u> (+)</u> by the Japanese. French brothers Joseph-Michel and Jacques-\u00c9tienne Montgolfier [[mohnt-gahl-FYEH]] undertook the first manned flight of this technology, which was used for reconnaissance at the Battle of (*) </b>Fleurus [[floo-ROO]]. For ten points, name these inflatable transports which Nadar used to take aerial photographs of Paris.", "answer": "Hot-Air <b><u>Balloon</u></b> (accept Fire <b><u>Balloon</u></b>; accept <b><u>Fu-Go</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The case</u> </b><em><b><u>[this U.S. state] v. Mitchell</u></b></em><b><u> held that the government could not force a</u></b> <b><u>state to lower the voting age to eighteen. This state's largest city performed a mock-</u><u>evacuation during Operation Greenlight after officials deemed the (+)</u> Willamette [[wih-LAM-et]] Valley a possible Soviet bombing target. In 2021, this state's eastern counties, including Malheur [[MALL-heer]], Sherman, and Grant, passed a measure promoting secession to form \"Greater (*) </b>Idaho.\" For ten points, name this U.S. state governed from Salem.", "answer": "<b><u>Oregon</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Myths about this location were discredited by Frantz Funck-Brentano [[foonk-</u><u>bren-TAH-noh]]. A large plaster elephant was placed at this location by Napoleon,</u></b> <b><u>though it was replaced by the July Column. (+)</u> Palloy the Patriot demolished this location, which was defended by Bernard Rene de Launay [[reh-neh-duh-law-NAY]] alongside the Swiss Guard who were cut down by a (*) </b>mob. For ten points, name this Parisian fortress and prison destroyed at the beginning of the French Revolution.", "answer": "The <b><u>Bastille</u></b> Saint-Antoine", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>The largest bronze example of this type of artwork depicts the controversial</u></b> <b><u>conquistador who committed a massacre of the Acoma Pueblo, Governor Juan de</u></b> <b><u>O\u00f1ate [[oh-NYAH-teh]]. One sculpture of this type known as the \"Quadriga,\" (*)</u></b> <b>depicting a vehicle driven by the Goddess of Victory, tops the Brandenburg Gate. Frederic Remington's </b><em><b>Bronco Buster</b></em><b>, a sculpture of this type, depicts a (*) </b>cowboy of the Old West. Ancient Greece's <em>Rampin Rider</em> is an early example of, for ten points, what type of statue?", "answer": "<b><u>Equestrian</u></b> Statue (accept answers describing subjects \"being on <b><u>horse</u></b>back\"; accept <b><u>Chariot</u></b> Statue)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>Fears of this person's influence led people to believe that Black men would</u></b> <b><u>knock down white women on this person's \"Tuesdays.\" Pauli Murray and this person</u></b> <b><u>worked to appeal for Odell Waller, though he was still executed in Virginia. Mary (+)</u></b> <b>McLeod Bethune and this person often walked arm-in-arm. This woman resigned from the Daughters of the American Revolution after Marian (*) </b>Anderson was not allowed to sing in Constitution Hall. For ten points, name this Depression-era First Lady.", "answer": "<b><u>Eleanor Roosevelt</u></b> (or Anna <b><u>Eleanor Roosevelt</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A character in this novel, based on a historical warlord also known as Xuande</u></b> <b><u>[[SHWAHN-DEH]], throws his infant son to the ground after General Zhao Yun</u></b> <b><u>[[ZHOW-YUN]] risks his life to save him during the Battle of (+)</u> Changban [[CHAHNG-BAHN]]. The Battle of Red Cliffs appears in this novel which relates the campaigns of Cao Cao [[KOW-KOW]] (*) </b>and Zhuge Liang [[TCHOO-guh LYAHNG]]. Luo Guanzhong [[LWOH GWAHN-ZHOHNG]] wrote, for ten points, what historical \u201cRomance\u201d set during a namesake period of Chinese history?", "answer": "<em><b><u>Romance of the Three Kingdoms</u></b></em> (or <em><b><u>S\u0101ngu\u00f3 Y\u01ceny\u00ec</u></b></em>)", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "<b><u>A member of this dynasty secretly renounced the throne in 1823, though a</u></b> <b><u>contingent of soldiers attempted to press his claim anyway, resulting in the</u></b> <b><u>Decembrist Revolt. In 1613 a</u> </b><em><b><u>zemsky sobor</u></b></em><b><u> elected Michael (+)</u> as the first ruler from this dynasty, ending the Time of Troubles. This house's last tsar was executed alongside his entire family in 1918 (*) </b>by Bolshevik soldiers. For ten points, name this long-time ruling house of the Russian empire.", "answer": "<b><u>Romanov</u></b> (or <b><u>Romanov</u></b>y; or <b><u>Romanov</u></b>s)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}